<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
	<!ENTITY rfc5234 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc3986 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc2560 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6960.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc5019 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5019.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc5280 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml'>
	<!ENTITY rfc4501 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4501.xml'>
]>

<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-pala-odin-03" ipr="trust200902">
    
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="5"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

  <front>
  <title abbrev="OOD">OCSP over DNS (ODIN)</title>
  <author initials="M.P." surname="Pala" fullname="Massimiliano Pala">
    <organization>CableLabs</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street>858 Coal Creek Cir</street>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <region>CO</region>
        <code>80027</code>
        <country>US</country>
      </postal>
      <email>m.pala@cablelabs.com</email>
      <uri>http://www.linkedin.com/in/mpala</uri>
    </address>
  </author>
 
  <date month="November" year="2017" />
  <area>Security</area>
  <workgroup></workgroup>
  <keyword>PKI</keyword>
  <keyword>Revocation</keyword>
  <keyword>OCSP</keyword>
  <abstract>
    <t>
    	With the increase number of protocols and applications that rely on digital certificates
    	to authenticate either the communication channel (TLS) or the data itself (PKIX), the need
    	for providing an efficient revocation system is paramount. Although the Online
    	Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP) allows for efficient lookup of
    	the revocation status of a certificate, the distribution of this information via HTTP (or
    	very rarely) HTTPS is not particularly efficient for high volume websites without incurring
    	in high distribution costs (e.g., CDN).
    
   		<vspace blankLines="1" />

   		In particular, this specification defines how to distribute OCSP responses over DNS
   		and how to define OCSP-over-DNS URLs in certificates.

   		The use of the DNS system to distribute such information is meant to lower the costs of
   		providing revocation services (by leveraging the distributed nature of DNS cache) and
   		increase the availability of revocation information (by providing an additional access
   		method for revocation information retrieval). 
   </t>
  </abstract>
</front>

<middle>

	<section title="Requirements notation">
		<t>
			The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
			"SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
			and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
			described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction"> 
		<t>
			With the increasing number of highly available and highly utilized websites that 
			require secure communications to protect the flow of information from the server 
			to the client and the raising number of devices (IoT) that require strong authentication
			capabilities, the need for a low-cost efficient approach to revocation information 
			availability is	crucial.

			The OCSP-over-DNS approach allows clients to determine the revocation status of digital
			certificates by optimizing the delivery mechanism for revocation information
			distribution to the client.
			This transport protocol can be used in lieu of or in addition to other PKIX endorsed
			transport mechanisms such as HTTP.

			This specification addresses the problem of providing a highly-available distributed system
			for OCSP responses <xref target="RFC6960" />.
			
			<vspace blankLines="1" />

			This document defines the DNS records to be used for OCSP data publication and the
			definition of additional URLs for the AuthorityInfoAccess (AIA) extension in certificates.

<!--
One solution is to provide a small response that can fit into a single UDP datagram.    Data signed (chain needs to be short.)    While the theoretical limit of a UDP datagram is 65,535 bytes (8 byte header + 65527 bytes of data), the generally accepted payload size for a UDP packet is 512 bytes.  (If a packet is broken up then you get problems associated with fragmentation, etc.)  For example, DNS is provided via UDP with a packet size of 512 bytes, and many applications set 512 bytes as the limit.  
Sign data that the client can provide, using the same approach you don’t have to include the chain 
-->
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="existing_solutions" title="Overview of existing solutions">
		<t>
			Currently there are three main options to retrieve the revocation information associated
			with a digital certificates:

			<list style="symbols">
   				<t>by retrieving the freshest CRL</t>
   				<t>by querying an OCSP responder for a freshly computed response</t>
   				<t>by retrieving a pre-signed OCSP response from a web site
      			   (typically a content distribution network or CDN)</t>
      			<t>by verifying pre-computed OCSP responses embedded (stapled) during
      			   the TLS negotiation (only in the TLS case, though)</t>
      		</list>

			All of these methods are based on the ability from the application to
			extract URLs out of the CRL (CrlDistributionPoint) or of the OCSP
			responder (AuthorityInfoAccess) from the certificate and query
			(almost uniquely via HTTP/HTTPS, although supported protocols might
			include LDAP and FTP) the corresponding server to retrieve the
			required data.
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="scope" title="Scope Statement">
		<t>
			This document focuses only on the definition of the required options
			for providing OCSP responses over DNS as an alternative transport
			protocol.  The reliability and accessibility of DNS records (e.g.,
			issues related to TCP vs. UDP DNS responses) are out of the scope of
			this document.
		</t>
	</section>

	<section title="Protocol Overview">
		<t>
			In order to validate a certificate using OCSP-over-DNS, the client should
			check the certificate for a DNS-based OCSP URI ("dns://") and then retrieve
			the OCSP response from the DNS.
			After this point, all procedures are to be performed according to the OCSP
			protocol as defined in <xref target="RFC5019"/>.
   
			In particular, clients using OCSP-over-DNS, SHOULD:
			<list style="numbers">
				<t> 
					Lookup the OCSP URI provided in the AIA of the certificate to be checked.
					The format of the URI comprises the id-ad-ocsp identifier and a base URL
					where the scheme (``dns://'') is used.
					The format of the full URI is discussed in <xref target="uri" />.
				</t>
				<t>
					Retrieve the DNS record carrying the required OCSP response.
				</t>
			</list>
 
		</t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="ocsprr" title="The OCSP Resource Record (OCSPRR)">
		<t>
			The OCSP DNS resource record (RR) is used to distribute a certificate's
			revocation status to clients.  The contents of the OCSP RR record are
			described in <xref target="rdata" />. 
		</t>
		
		<t>
			The type value for the OCSP RR type is defined in <xref target="rtype" />.
		</t>
		
		<t>
   			The OCSP RR is class independent.
   		</t>

   		<t>
   			The OCSP RR Time to Live (TTL) should not exceed the validity period
   			of the OCSP response that is contained in the record.
   		</t>

		<section anchor="rdata" title="The OCSP RDATA Wire Format">
			<t>
				The RDATA for an OCSP RR consists of a single field which carries the
				DER encoded OCSP response for the identified certificate.
			</t>
    <figure><artwork>
                         1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 2 3 3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |                                                               /
    +                       OCSP Response Data                      /
    /                                                               /
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    </artwork></figure>

      		<t>
      			The OCSP response should contain only one response that refers to the
      			certificate which contains that URL.  Following this schema, the OCSP
      			DNS URIs within the AIA extension SHOULD be unique for each certificate
      			issued by a single CA.
			</t>

		</section>

		<section anchor="rtype" title="The OCSP RRType">
			<t>
				This document uses a new DNS RR type, OCSP, whose value (TBD) was
				allocated by IANA from the Resource Record (RR) TYPEs subregistry of
				the Domain Name System (DNS) Parameters registry.
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="time" title="Time Validity">
			<t>
				The time validity should reflect the frequency of updates in revocation
				information (i.e., the TTL should not be set to expire after the OCSP
				response expiration). In practice, as an operational matter, operators
				SHOULD ensure that the records are published in a way that the TTL is
				low enough that they expire from caches before the OCSP response
				expiration.
			</t>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section anchor="uri" title="Specifying DNS URLs for OCSP RR">
		<t>
			The Authority Information Access extension, as defined in <xref target="RFC5280" />,
			provides information about the certificate in which the extension appears.  In order
			to specify the availability of OCSP responses over DNS, Certification Authorities
			should use the OCSP accessMethod OID (id-ad-ocsp) and use "dns" as the transport.
   		</t>
   			<!-- @deprecated: The use of a new OID for DNS-based is not required as the URI
   			                  already contains the transport -->
   			<!--
   			The new access method OID is defined as follows:
   		</t>
   		<figure><artwork>
      id-ad-ocsp-dns OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::= { id-ad 3 }
        </artwork></figure>

		<t>
			When the id-ad-ocsp-dns appears as accessMethod, the accessLocation field
			describes the location of the OCSP response related to the certificate the
			extension appears in and its syntax should follow the specifications in
			<xref target="RFC4501" /> for DNS URIs.
		</t>
		-->
		<t>
			Please note that, when using this accessMethod, the use of the dnsathority
			in the specified URI is discouraged as this might reduce the benefits coming
			from the caching infrastructure of DNS and, possibly, overload the referred
			DNS server.
		</t>

		<section anchor="urldef" title="URL definition">
			<t>
				A DNS URL <xref target="RFC3986" /> begins with the protocol prefix "dns"
				and is defined by the following grammar, following the ABNF notation defined in
				<xref target="RFC5234"/>.
			</t>

			<figure><artwork>
      dnsurl = scheme COLON SLASH SLASH [target]
              [QUESTION [ TYPE=rr_type ]
              ; target: is the dns entry for
              ; the lookup operation.
              ; rr_type: is the type of record
              ; to be retrieved. If not specified,
              ; the default type is OCSPRR

      scheme  = "dns"
  
      SLASH       = %x2F              ; forward slash ("/")
      COLON       = %x3A              ; colon (":")
      QUESTION    = %x3F              ; question mark ("?")
      TYPE        = "type"            ; the keyword ("type")
            </artwork></figure>

            <!-- @deprecated: the distinction between "dns" and "dnssec" is irrelevant
                              at the application layer -->
            <!--
			<t>
				The "dns" prefix indicates an entry or entries accessible from the
				configured DNS server. The "dnssec" prefix indicates, instead, an entry or
				entries that are expected to be accessible via the DNSSEC protocol and
				verification of the returned data SHOULD be performed at the resolver level.
				Applications capable of correctly process DNSSEC authentication information
				MAY also verify the returned data authenticity. However, given the fact that
				the retrieved data already carries its own authentication, this step is not
				required at the application level.
			</t>
			-->

			<t>
				Although this specification does not mandate for any specific format for the
				&lt;target&gt; component of the DNS URL, some examples are provided in <xref target="uri_samples" />
				with the intent to illustrate, not define, the format.
			</t>

		</section>

		<!-- @deprecated: the suggestion about using TXT might confuse deployers and then applications
		                  will have to support multiple records types. Removed as suggested by DNSOP -->
		<!--
		<section anchor="txt_records" title="Use of TXT Records">
			<t>
				Although conforming CAs SHOULD use OCSP RR for distributing OCSP responses via DNS, to allow
				for early adoption of the transport mechanism, CAs MAY use TXT records for this purpose.

				In this case, CAs shall use ``TXT'' as the &gt;type&lt; component of the DNS URL and MUST
				base64 encode the value of the OCSP responses when adding them to the corresponding DNS
				entry.

				Conforming clients MAY support the ``TXT'' record type and MUST support the ``OCSPRR''
				record type for the retrieval of OCSP responses via DNS.
			</t>
		</section>
		-->

		<section anchor="uriproc" title="DNS URL Processing">
			<t>
				In order to process the OCSP DNS URLs in a certificate, clients have to extract the &lt;target&gt;
				and, if provided, the &lt;type&gt; of record from the URL. After that, client MUST query for the
				specified record.
					
				When the ``OCSPRR'' record type is used, the returned value MUST contain the DER encoded
				OCSP response related to the certificate that the client is going to validate.

				<!-- @deprecated -->
				<!--
				When the ``TXT'' record type is used, the returned value MUST contain the base64 representation
				of the DER encoded OCSP response related to the certificate that the client is going to validate.
				-->
			</t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="uri_samples" title="OCSPRR URI Examples">
			<t>
				When using the issuing CA's DNS sub-domain in the DNS URL, the hex (or decimal) representation
				of the certificate's serialNumber MAY be used as the hostname of the DNS URL. 
				When combined with the specific sub-domain of the issuing CA this provides a unique
				entry that can be easily queried. For example, given that the sub-domain of the
				issuing CA is "ca1.example.com", the resulting URL in the issued certificate can
				be constructed as follows:
			</t>
			<figure><artwork>
      dns://04A3E45534A1B5.ca1.example.com?type=OCSPRR
            </artwork></figure>

			<t>
				Because the serialNumber of a certificate is guaranteed to be unique within a (single) CA,
				different Certification Authorities MUST use different sub-domains when using this publication
				algorithm to avoid collisions across different CAs. 
			</t>
			<t>
				However, in some environments, the serial number that will be used in the certificate to be
				issued can not be pre-fetched and embedded in the AIA's DNS URL entry. In this case, the use of
				a monotonically increasing or random integer number can be used instead.
			</t>
			<t>
				In any case, it is important to notice that since the DNS entry is to be used "AS IS" by the
				relying party that wants to fetch the OCSP response by using the DNS URL, other techniques (e.g.,
				the use of prefixes for different issuing CAs combined with high-resolution clock entries
				and small random or monotonic integer suffixes) can be implemented independently by different
				Certificate Service Providers.
			</t>

		</section>

	</section>

	<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
		<t>
			This document uses a new DNS RR type, OCSPRR, whose value (TBD) MUST be allocated by IANA from
			the Resource Record (RR) TYPEs subregistry of the Domain Name System (DNS) Parameters registry.
		</t>
	</section>


	<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
		<t>
			Several security considerations need to be explicitly considered for the system administrators
			and application developers to understand the weaknesses of the overall architecture.

			It is important to highlight, however, that the following considerations are inherently derived
			from the nature of the DNS infrastructure and that deployment of the DNSSEC protocol might
			provide an efficient protection against them.
		</t>

		<t>
			By lacking the ability to authenticate the originating server directly, the DNS (not DNSSEC)
			protocol (both in TCP and UDP mode) is vulnerable to attacks where false responses are provided.

			Although all the information stored in the OCSP RR is signed, the data returned to the client
			could potentially be altered (e.g., by providing an empty or old response). This type of attack
			can lead to the application's inability to retrieve the revocation information, thus this
			approach is vulnerable to Denial of Service (DoS), Man-in-the-middle (MITM), and Reply Attacks.
		</t>
		<t>
			As mentioned earlier, the deployment of DNSSEC can help in mitigating the described family of
			attacks by providing a mean for the client (or its resolver) to verify signatures of the DNS
			records themselves via the DNS keys.

			This said, the use of DNS (instead of DNSSEC) is equivalent, from a security considerations
			point of view, to today's deployment best practices for OCSP where pre-computed responses are
			delivered by CDNs via HTTP (not HTTPS).

			Therefore, the provisioning of OCSP responses via DNS does not lower or alter the security
			considerations that apply to the use of OCSP.

			Last but not least, because of the availability (in most cases) of independent DNS servers that
			an application can query, the use of multiple requests to different DNS servers (for the same
			DNS record) might be implemented as a mitigating measure in case an attack is suspected or
			detected.
		</t>

	</section>

	<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments">
		<t>
			The authors would like to thank everybody who provided insightful comments and helped in the
			definition of the deployment considerations. In particular, the authors would like to thank
			Scott A. Rea for his support. We also would like to thank DigiCert and the initial discussion
			and support for the initial idea. Last but not least, the authors would like to thank all
			the people that expressed interest in implementing support for this proposal.
		</t>
	</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title='Normative References'>

&rfc5234;
&rfc3986;
&rfc2119;
&rfc2560;
&rfc5019;
&rfc5280;
&rfc4501;

</references>

</back>
</rfc>



